hi today I would like to talk about
something that I have written about in
the past under the heading of the war on
sense-making so let's frame it like this
for a very long period of time as far as
I can tell us least as long as since
that giant obelisk helped chimpanzees
figure out how to kill each other with
bones we've been working on different
ways to become more effective at killing
each other with weapons and yet at the
same time there was a particular moment
when the combination between our
incessant drive to figure out how to
blow each other up met with a new set of
innovations in science most notably
physics and chemistry and in economy
most notably the industrial economy to
create a distinctly new capacity along
this long history of figuring out how to
kill each other
and this new capacity accelerated
through the 19th and 20th centuries
until it it reached what seems to have
been a peak roughly in the 1950s where
with the invention of the hydrogen bomb
we had reached the the singular moment
where we had the capacity to in fact
extinct ourselves as a species and
possibly cleanse the entire globe of
biological life and the point being that
that was both a function of a particular
combination of capacities and the
cessation to a greater or lesser extent
of a particular arc in the history of
war which is to say that for sure we
have continued to complete the set in
all the different tools in the toolkit
of how to kill each other but everything
kind of pales in comparison to mass
nuclear holocaust now within that same
notion all right the idea of there being
a very long arc and yet there being
shifting capabilities which has led to
an acceleration I'd like to then
consider a different story
I'm very closely allied story which is
to say that for a very long period of
time people have noticed that there is a
way to achieve differential individual
advantage by being good at lying to
manipulating and deceiving other people
and of course this fact has shown up in
various kinds of technologies of this
type forever and yet round about the the
turn of the 20th century round about the
point at which the the arc of weapons of
mass destruction was beginning to reach
its apex we entered into a new triangle
in this case the sciences had turned
from outward physics and chemistry to
inward psychology cognitive neuroscience
neuroscience itself the the economy had
in turn turned from industrialization
and the deployment of energy to
commercialization and the creation of
the consumer culture and war had turned
into the war on sense-making now and in
just the same way as the previous war
once that triangle had been established
accelerated from musket to nuke my
proposition is that something similar to
that has actually happened in the domain
of the were on sense-making and this is
where things get interesting
well it is daunting to be present to the
explosive destructive capacities of a
hydrogen bomb it is at least obvious by
contrast an accelerating capacity in a
war on sense-making is by definition
increasingly a cult let me put this a
slightly different way in the 1970s for
a variety of reasons
we specifically the people of the United
States became aware of certain
activities that had been undertaken
largely but not exclusively by the CIA
as their part in the Cold War portion of
the war on sense-making one piece of
this uncovering was part of something
called the Church Commission now in the
church commission we became aware of the
fact that the CIA had been doing things
that had not been known before and oddly
enough are broadly not well understood
now and we're gonna get into that in a
second
but things like a project called MKULTRA
another one called Mockingbird
Northwoods paperclip all of which are or
were real meaning that they're not made
up sophisticated command and substantial
resources and clearly involved
researching how to more fully extend and
develop capacities in the war on
sense-making none of this is to say that
the CIA is or was particularly either
malevolent or uniquely skillful in this
proceeding after all there was a war on
and war is a competition and in
competition you work hard to be more
effective than those with whom you're
competing and there's an interesting
characteristic that I don't think is
fully grasped enough which is that
innovation is hard and copying is easy
and so when you're engaged in a
competition along the threshold of
innovation
this puts a premium on being skillful at
innovation pushing the state of the art
forward but also has this interesting
consequence that all of your competitors
more or less get your innovation for
free to the degree which they can
identify what it was they can copy it
and then the state of the field moves
right so this actually pushes the entire
field forward along the threshold
innovation so for example it was really
hard to invent the atomic bomb but two
years after we had done that the Soviets
had copied it or whatever a few years
after he'd done that now part of that
was through the use of espionage but
doesn't matter the point is that
innovation is hard and copying is easy
however did you do about doing your copy
the point being that one we can imagine
that the CIA was part of a larger field
of play of many different agents of whom
the KGB was certainly a key piece but
not the only who are all exploring the
overall space of the war on sense-making
and every single time any of them made
any meaningful form of innovation
each would endeavor to copy that and
move the field of play forward so this
then has an implication when we look at
the state of the art as we were able to
see it to degree which by the way that
was a valid seeing at all we saw
something it's not clear we saw
everything
yeah the Church Commission the state of
the art in the mid 70s of the CIA
we should propose that that state of the
art was broadly shared by many other
players and even to the degree to which
we might imagine that the various laws
that were passed restricting CIA
activity in the 70s had any impact you
know obviously those didn't have any
impact on the rest of the folks in the
more on sense making so this the field
of play would have continued to
accelerate and so we have a
we haven't actually had a caller ping or
a discovery of the current state of the
art of the various taking tools and
techniques and the one since making it
since then so for 40 years or so
something's been going on and we don't
really have any insight into what that
something is
and yet if the if the model is even
vaguely like the model that was proposed
with regard to weapons of mass
destruction you might say that the
seventies may be represented world war 1
and in that start which is to say the
very beginning of the introduction of
airplanes and tanks large cannons in
trench warfare and that we should expect
to be somewhere around the introduction
of the atomic bomb and the war on
sense-making and it's not clear exactly
what that is does that make sense
the point being if you aren't right now
wondering how effective various
potential agents are at deception
manipulation confusion then either you
have an uniquely high capacity to endure
uncertainty or you're not really
thinking clearly about the implications
of the whirlen sense-making and then the
final point well weapons of mass
destruction are quite problematic and
the ability to actually deploy
destruction at a level that could
extinguish the species is quite a bit of
a problem their moral equivalent in the
domain of sense-making
is substantially worse as mentioned for
example at the very least weapons of
mass destruction are obvious so we can
see them and we can feel them and we can
we can sense the the dangers that they
pose and therefore endeavour to respond
to them the the web
of the war on sense-making are
destructive precisely to that capacity
we cannot see them we cannot make sense
of them we cannot understand them
therefore we cannot respond to them past
a certain threshold we may in fact be so
fully removed from our ability to make
sense that we will be simply incapable
of responding to them and so if you if
you feel like the combination between
commercial technology and that degree of
human endeavor that has carefully
figured out how to convince someone that
making a choice between peppermint soap
and spearmint soap is a meaningful
choice the entire set of science is
associated with how human beings go
about using mind in the world and the
military industrial complex you're right
and getting a hold of that and a grasp
of that is a big piece of any valid
strategy in the contemporary environment